In this world, there are many unseen Pokémon
which have only been spoken of in folklore.
This book contains the author's depictions
of many such Pokémon.
Is that the one you're searching for, Papa?
Yes. Papa has been searching for it a long time.
The mysterious Pokémon, Unknown.
I...
I like this one.
The phantom Pokémon, Entei.
Your favourite, Mī...
Entei is strong and kind.
Just like you, Papa.
Papa's like Entei, huh? I hope I am.
That settles it! Papa is Entei!
It's Entei!
All right, we're off!
Mail?
It must be yours, Papa.
I think it's important.
It's John.
Sir, we've found clues relating to
Unknown in the ruins.
Please come as soon as possible.
Clues relating to Unknown?
It really was about work.
I'm sorry, Mī.
I'll be back as soon as I can.
Papa...
Good night, Mī...
It's here, Professor Sully.
We've never seen these letters before,
but we believe the text is about the Unknown.
Incredible!
You're the only one
who can decipher it, sir.
What the...?
Unknown...
Sir?
Professor Sully?
Professor!
The young miss is truly alone now...
Papa, are you back?
Mī...
Young Miss...
Papa...
Please mail me.
Unknown?
Papa...
Are these for me?
I'm so lonely, Papa...
Unknown...
Would you like to play with me?
What's this?
Young Miss!
Those are Unknown!
Hey!
Papa...
Papa... come back to me...
Were you the one who called me?
Entei?
I am... Entei.
Papa... You're Papa, aren't you?
You became an Entei and
came back to me! Papa!
Papa...
I am Papa...
I shall grant your wish.
Having traveled far
from his hometown, Masara Town,
Satoshi aims to enter the
Johto League with his friends.
Their training journey
continues today.
You're a Pokémon Trainer, aren't you?
Yeah. I'm Satoshi from Masara Town.
I'm aiming to become a Pokémon Master.
I'm Takeshi, my lady!
What's your name?
My name's Lynn.
Well? Want to battle?
How about it?
What are you gonna do, Satoshi?
It's common courtesy to
accept a call to battle, of course!
Thanks!
Let's give it our all as trainers!
Okay!
Let's battle!
OK!
OK! Let's move on!
OK! tsugi ni susumou ze!
OK! Together, we'll be all right!
OK! issho nara daijoubu!
OK! Though the wind may change...
OK! kaze ga kawatte mo
OK! ...my dream is unchanging!
OK! kawaranai ano yume!
We've been so focused on making it this far...
koko made kuru no ni muchuu sugite
...that we didn't even notice...
kizukazu ni ita keredo
...that we'd already obtained the key...
atarashii sekai e no tobira no kagi wa
...to the door leading to the new world!
shiranai uchi ni get shite ita yo
Golden Smile & Silver Tears
Delight and frustration...
yorokobi to kuyashisa to
...are always changing faces...
kawari banko ni kao dashite
...and making everyone stronger!
minna o tsuyoku shite kureteru yo
OK! Follow me!
OK! ore ni tsuite koi!
OK! My spirit will never falter!
OK! kiai nara makenai ze!
OK! Even if we crash into a wall...
OK! kabe ni butsukatte mo
OK! ...this journey won't end!
OK! owaranai kono tabi!
It's not as though there haven't been times...
akirame kaketari shita koto mo
...where I felt ready to give it up
nakatta wake ja nai keredo
But the me from the day I set off, burning with anticipation...
tabidachi no ano asa no moeteru ore ga
...asks "Are you really okay with that?"
sore de ii no ka to toi kakete kuru yo
Golden Sun & Silver Moon
The sun and moon...
ohisama to otsukisama
...are always changing faces...
kawari banko ni kao dashite
...and watching over everyone!
minna o mimamotte kureteru yo
And so...
dakara
OK! Swallow your fear!
OK! fuan nante tabechaou!
OK! Use your best move: "Bravado"!
OK! jiman no waza "karagenki"
OK! Though I don't know their names or voices,
OK! namae mo koe mo shiranai
they're waiting for me!
aitsura ga matteru hazu!
I want to meet them!
aitsura ni aitain da!
Let's go!
iku ze
OK! Let's open the next door!
OK! tsugi no tobira akeyou ze!
OK! Use your best move: "Recklessness"!
OK! jiman no waza "mukoumizu"
OK! My friends, with whom I've shared laughter and tears...
OK! issho ni naite waratta
are here by my side!
nakama tachi ga tsuite iru!
I believe in them!
nakama tachi o shinjiteru!
OK!!
You guys are pretty strong.
We need to do more training!
Nah, we were really struggling.
That was your fifth battle this week.
Your Pokémon must be tired.
Yeah...
Lynn, do you happen to know if
there's a Pokémon Center nearby?
There's one in Greenfield,
just past this forest.
"Greenfield"? You mean...
The location named as the number one place
for girls to visit in the Johto Region?!
Bingo!
I'm headed there, too.
Greenfield...
A lush, peaceful place.
They say the wind that blows through it
can calm the hearts of both people and Pokémon.
I've always wanted to go there!
The number one place for girls to visit...
So many ladies...
Greenfield's just past that hill.
I am so glad we've been
chasing Pikachu!
We finally reached the place of my dreams, Greenfield, but... What's this?
Green? More like light.
Is this some kind of treasure?
Did somebody use Pay Day, meow?
Sonansu!
That's right!
You came out on your own again?!
Get back inside!
Miss Junsa...
Ready?
Okay.
Here we go.
Got it.
Three...
Two...
One...
Here we are in Greenfield, a peaceful town
renowned for its lush, green scenery...
...where an unprecedented phenomenon,
which must be seen to be believed, has occurred.
We believe this phenomenon
originates from Sully Snowdon's mansion,
but we do not yet know any details.
Sully Snowdon?
Professor Sully is well known throughout the world
for his research on Legendary Pokémon.
Wasn't Professor Sully
one of your students, Professor Okido?
Indeed, and a splendid one to boot!
Come to think of it, I was sent
a mail containing his latest thesis.
What's this?
It's Unknown.
Unknown?
Professor Okido,
did you see what was on TV?
I just watched it.
I'm about to head over there.
I'm going, too!
You knew Sully as well, didn't you?
His daughter is still young, so I'm worried.
Understood. We'll leave posthaste!
Got it!
Arriving here now
at the Greenfield Pokémon Center...
...are a group ready to
take hold of the situation.
Professor Okido,
we've been waiting for you.
Professor...
Oh, Pikachu!
Mom!
Oh, Satoshi.
What's this? You kids are here, too?
Long time no see, Professor Okido!
I figured you'd make it here.
Have you been doing well, Satoshi?
Yeah. How about you?
Papa...
I want a Mama, too...
If that's what you wish, Mī.
Long ago, Professor Sully was
studying under Professor Okido.
Didn't you say he used to help
you with your homework?
Yeah.
He's visited Masara Town
a few times since then.
I see, so that was him.
That's Professor Sully's house.
I'm really worried...
Me, too.
What's wrong, Pikachu?
What?!
A Pokémon?!
I've never seen anything like it before!
Who are you?
Mama... You are... Mama.
You are Mama!
I am... Mama...
I am... Mama.
Hey, wait!
Mom! Pikachu!
Enough!
Pikachu! Are you okay?
Stay back, Satoshi!
You don't know what's in there!
Why? Why my mom?!
I've brought her to you.
The one you wished for.
Mama...
Mama!
I am... Mama...
Mama, I'm here! It's Mī.
Mī...
Mama...
Now I can be with Papa and Mama forever.
Yes.
If that is what you wish.
Your world continues to expand.
Pretty...
If you are happy, then so am I.
The Pokémon who
kidnapped Satoshi's mom...
It was Entei.
Entei?
It's only been spoken of in legends.
There's another mysterious Pokémon
involved in this case, too.
Unknown, correct?
The one you've been researching.
The Unknown are inside that mansion.
I see...
Just as I thought.
Right now at Greenfield,
the site of the mysterious sprawling crystal formation,
we're told that the Pokémon who
kidnapped the female bystander is known as Entei.
Mom! Pikachu!
However, details of the event
are currently unknown.
A bulldozer has just arrived
to clear through the crystals.
You can't!
Don't destroy it!
Professor Sully's disappearance,
this mysterious crystallization,
and even the sudden arrival of Entei...
All of it was caused by the Unknown.
I can't imagine any other explanation.
Mail?
Papa and Mama came back to me.
I'm happy now.
Everything is good!
So stay out!
Mī...
Her sending me this mail
must mean she's all right...
But this is strange.
Isn't her dad missing?
Yeah.
And when she said "Mama"...
Puzzling, to be sure.
Papa, your back is so big!
Are you having fun?
Yeah!
I can't wait around for them
to solve the puzzle!
You gonna come with me, Pikachu?
Wait, Satoshi!
I'm going, too!
Don't leave me behind, either!
Kasumi, Takeshi...
Is this...?
Satoshi, take that Pokégear with you.
Lynn...
Probably best to have a way of
communicating with the Pokémon Center, right?
I'll think of an excuse
to tell Professor Okido.
Thanks.
Water doesn't seem to crystallize...
Yeah. If we follow the river, we should be able to
find a way inside the Snowdon mansion.
Those guys never give up, meow.
We are Team Rocket,
aiming for outer space!
If going from below won't work,
we'll drop in from above!
Our goal: to take the castle's treasures!
What a great feeling!
What?
Isn't that the thing they were
talking about on TV?
Entei, right?
What an awful feel-
How cruel can you be to attack us
out of nowhere like that?!
At least we got ourselves inside, meow...
But what is this place?
Doesn't look like there's any treasure here.
Besides, any treasure worth having
should be carried on you at all times!
Does that mean the treasure's
in that tower, meow?
If we want to go to that tower...
We'll have to go down, then back up...
Easier said than done...
Do they not have an elevator?
Of course not, meow!
Who was that?
Nobody. We're the only ones here.
Mama, they're showing our house!
Isn't it pretty?
It is...
Something resembling a flame was just spotted
above the Snowdon mansion,
but we cannot confirm at this time.
A rescue squad is set to arrive
tomorrow morning, but...
Hm? Are those... Pokémon?
All right, Fushigidane, Chicorita!
Use Vine Whip!
Togepi, keep still for a bit, okay?
Satoshi?!
What is he doing?!
Um, actually...
It looks like someone is trying
to get into our house...
Satoshi...
How could you even think of doing
something so dangerous?!
What is it, Mama?
Nothing...
The thing on his back is a Pikachu, right?
Ah! He has a Fushigidane
and a Chicorita, too!
Mama, is he a Pokémon Trainer?
Yes...
Maybe he has other Pokémon, too!
Right, Papa?
Papa?
Thanks for the help, guys.
And thanks to you, too, Fushigidane and Chicorita.
You really came through for us!
Are you guys okay?
Lynn?
Satoshi, you were just on TV!
Sorry, Professor Okido.
But I...
I won't order you back after already making it there!
Just save your mother and hurry back!
Got it!
Satoshi, it's John.
Have you seen any Unknown?
No, not yet.
I see.
According to Professor Sully's research,
Unknown can sense the feelings of others.
What do you mean?
They can sense the feelings in people's hearts
and form reality from them.
They can sense the feelings
in our hearts?
I believe the Unknown are reacting
to the feelings in Mī's heart.
I'm certain the crystal tower was formed by
the Unknown reacting to her heart!
Hinoarashi, Flamethrower!
All right!
Try again!
Flamethrower!
Good job, Rokon!
All right, let's swap battlers!
Water Gun!
All right. Now, Pikachu.
Let's go, guys!
Hitodeman, good work!
You too, Waninoko. Well done!
What?
Is this what Professor Okido warned us about?
The power of the Unknown?
Probably...
Either way, we gotta keep moving!
What's going on?
It's the world that
the Unknown created from Mī's heart!
This is...
Ouch! Oww!
We finally reach the bottom,
and what do we find?
Are these Pokémon?
Best to steer clear of things
we don't understand, meow.
Well, yeah, but we have to get through here
to reach the other tower!
Then we'll just have to sneak by!
Quietly...
Quiet steps...
Stealthy steps...
Soft steps...
Quiet steps...
Stealthy steps...
Looks like that boy from earlier and his friends
got inside the house.
Should I remove them?
I want to face them in a Pokémon battle!
But do you think I can do it?
Of course you can.
If that is what you wish.
That's right! I can do it!
I'm still little, but...
When I grow up...
I can do it, right?
This will be my first Pokémon battle!
You can do it, Mī.
I can do it, right?
Entei?
The three of you are
Pokémon Trainers, right?
What's it to you?
Would you like to battle?
I don't know who you are,
but we don't have time for that right now.
How boring.
You, Entei over there!
Where did you take my mom?!
Only my parents and I are here!
That's right.
What?!
Satoshi...
Your name is Mī, right?
Oh, you know who I am?
Mī's much smaller than
that though, isn't she?
This is Mī's world, as created by
the power of the Unknown.
That girl can make and become
anything she wants!
No way...
Are we going to battle or not?
All right!
I'll be your opponent, miss!
Fine, then.
Takeshi?
Entei came from up there.
Your mom should be up there, too.
Let's go, Satoshi.
Finding your mom's our first priority!
Let's go, Pikachu!
We'll use three Pokémon each.
You're free to switch out
at any time, okay?
Understood.
Go, Zubat!
I'm counting on you!
Mokoko, go!
Zubat, use Supersonic!
It's working!
Zubat, Wing Attack!
Here it comes! Dodge it!
Good job! Here it comes again!
Use Headbutt!
Now! Thunder Shock!
Return, Zubat!
You did your best.
We did it!
That was amazing, Mokoko!
This match has only just begun!
Go, Rokon!
In that case...
How about this one?
A Himeguma, is it?
A cute Pokémon for a cute lady!
It isn't just cute.
Himeguma, Explosive Punch!
Rokon, use Lightning Speed!
Himeguma, Fury Swipes!
These pokémon were created
from Mī's heart...
They're a lot stronger than they look!
Soft steps, quiet steps,
stealthy steps...
Is there really any treasure here?
What are you blabbering about?
We can't go back empty-handed after all this!
Return, Rokon!
You're pretty strong!
You, too.
I may not look it, but I'm training to become
the world's greatest Pokémon Breeder!
Both trainers and Pokémon need
to be properly raised.
Need to be properly raised...
You're right!
Yeah, that smile!
That's a nice smile!
You're a strange one.
Gomazo, use Rollout!
You shouldn't take us lightly
just because we're small!
Mī, is this your picture book?
Yeah.
Papa used to read it to me
all the time...
I see...
You can have it if you want, Mama...
Mī, have you always been alone?
Did you start feeling lonely?
A little bit...
But it's okay now...
Mama and Papa are here...
So which of you will battle me now?
That must mean Takeshi...
Mī cannot possibly lose.
Is Entei an illusion, too?
I want to battle a stronger trainer.
What?
Satoshi, leave her to me.
And you are?
I'm the world's greatest beauty, Kasumi!
In a fair world, I would have been
the leader of Hanada Gym!
You're a Gym Leader?
Don't look down on me.
You don't have to be an adult
to be a Gym Leader?
You can be whatever you want to be.
Her real body is probably with your mom!
Hurry up to where she is!
I'm from Hanada Gym,
so I'll be using Water types!
Then I'll use Water-type Pokémon, too.
I see.
You can do anything here, huh?
Let's battle!
Here I go!
Kingdra, please!
Go, my steady!
All right!
Now go for a Headbutt!
Tosakinto, Fury Attack!
Tosakinto, you did your best...
We did it! We did it!
This one's next!
Not bad.
How is this even possible?
Don't waste time
with common sense! Just go!
We are Team Rocket,
aiming for outer space!
Just keep aiming higher!
Or something to that effect, meow!
Tackle!
Mantine, now use Whirlpool!
We're trapped!
Bubble Beam!
Hitodeman, Rapid Spin!
Well?
Amazing!
Mantine, Take Down!
Hitodeman, Tackle!
This is fun!
This is so much fun!
Nothing makes me happier
than seeing you smile.
Thank you, Papa.
Satoshi...
Mom, are you okay?
I'm fine.
But I can't believe you came all the way here...
You're still as reckless as ever.
It's because I'm your son!
Mī?
Yes.
What about Unknown?
...Not here?
If you mean the Pokémon that brought me here,
he left a while ago.
That was Entei.
This crystal tower and that Entei...
...were both created by Pokémon called Unknown,
who sensed what Mī wanted.
Impossible...
Anyway, let's get out of here!
All right.
Wake up...
Wake up, Mī.
What's wrong, Mama?
Listen, Mī.
I'm not your real mother.
I'm Satoshi's mother. Not yours.
Do you remember who I am, Mī?
We met in Masara Town.
Please, come with me.
Mama...
You can't stay here!
No...
No!
Mom... Mom!
Mom, are you okay?
Yes...
Mom, this way!
What is the matter, Mī?
Papa, that boy wants
to take Mama away!
Satoshi!
Mom! Mom!
Leave her and go!
I could never do that!
She's my mom!
She is Mī's mother here.
You can't just decide that!
Get out.
If you refuse to leave on your own,
I will make you leave!
We'll see about that!
Waninoko, I choose you!
You think you can defeat me?
I won't lose to an illusion!
Waninoko, Water Gun!
I'm an illusion, you say?
Nonsense!
Return, Waninoko!
If water won't work,
let's try fire!
Go, Hinoarashi!
Hinoarashi, Flamethrower!
Return, Hinoarashi!
He's strong...
Do you still believe me
to be an illusion?
You're an illusion of Entei
created by that girl's heart!
No...
No!
I'm a mere illusion, am I?
I am... I am...
...this girl's father!
Pikachu!
Mī, you need to remember...
Remember your real
Papa and Mama!
Mī!
We finally made it!
Here, too?
A battle, meow?
And we're caught in the middle...
Pikachu!
Lizardon!
Lizardon, you're here!
Thank you!
Satoshi!
Are you all right?
What is that?
My friend!
Friend?
My Pokémon are all friends
I've made on my journey!
Friends...?
I care not how many
of them there are!
We're...
...your friends too, aren't we?!
Takeshi! Kasumi!
Before you even ask us
about "this" or "that"...
Musashi!
Kojiro!
And Nyarth!
We're your friends
from Team Rocket!
Team Rocket?
Why are you...?
Actually...
Somehow...
Our hands happened to reach out.
We may be enemies,
but we got history together, meow.
Come on, Mī. Come with us.
My friends are here!
Go away!
Lizardon!
Papa!
Do you really think
you can be Mī's father?
As long as she wishes it,
I will be Mī's father!
Mī!
Lizardon, Flamethrower!
Lizardon, do it again!
Papa!
Lizardon, Fire Spin!
Entei, please! Listen to me!
If you really care about Mī,
then listen to me!
You can't stay here with her!
It's not right!
Be that as it may,
I desire to grant Mī's wishes!
Lizardon!
If you keep her here,
she'll always be alone!
Lizardon...
This is the end!
Stop!
Papa, stop... No more!
No more of this!
Mī, I lost against you.
Your Gomazo's Rollout
was really strong!
Your Mantine's Whirlpool, too!
You could be a Gym Leader one day!
After a battle ends,
us trainers
who love Pokémon...
We stay good friends.
Let's go outside.
Even if you fight outside...
You can make friends.
Lots of them.
Let's go, Mī.
It's warm...
Papa?
I was born to be a father
with the sole desire to make you happy.
If your happiness
lies in the outside world...
Then I...
What?
Wha...?
What now?!
This way!
Lizardon, take care of Mī!
Hold on tight!
Everybody, hurry!
Professor, what's going on?
It's the Unknown!
They're no longer able to control
the power they've unleashed!
The crystallization is
rapidly approaching!
Satoshi, you have to stop
the Unknown from running wild!
Got it!
The crystallization is
spreading further!
Even the Pokémon Center is
being engulfed by it!
Run away!
Y-Yes!
Hurry!
These are the Unknown...
How do we stop them?
There's a barrier protecting them!
Lizardon, go!
It's working!
Pikachu, I'm counting on you!
100,000 Volts!
Pikachu, are you all right?
Isn't this, like, really bad?
Doesn't look like there's any treasure, either,
so let's just go home, meow!
Yeah, let's...
Excuse us...
We're blocked in, meow!
Somebody do something!
Unknown, please stop!
Mī...
It brought me much happiness...
...to have been your father.
The last thing I can do for you...
...is to take you from this place.
Papa...
I was born of your dreams.
If you believe in me,
there is nothing I cannot do.
Papa...!
Mī... Mī!
Mī, you have to believe in Entei!
Believe your Entei can't lose!
You can do it, Papa!
Mī...
Mī!
Papa...
Thank you for calling me Papa.
I shall return to your dreams.
Papa...
This is the real...
Greenfield!
It's beautiful!
Hey, are you youngsters safe?
Professor Okido!
Lynn!
Here I am!
Thank you...
Let's go meet them, Mī.
Everyone was worried about you!
Come on.
Yeah!
Mī!
Young Miss!
Well? What should we do now?
The ground's crawling with police officers.
Couldn't go down there if we wanted to...
In any case...
That's one less lonely girl, meow!
But there's another in here!
A young, lonely girl...
Musashi!
And a young man taking a stand
against loneliness...
Kojiro!
The moon's always on its own, meow!
Behold! The wind blows
through Greenfield!
Even if you're alone,
we'll be your friends!
Somehow, this is a really...
...great feeling!
ame wa yagate agaru mono
Before long, the rain will stop falling
kumo wa itsuka kireru mono
Someday, the clouds will disperse
kao o agete goran
Go on and look up,
kimi o yobu koe kikoeru hazu
and you will hear a voice calling out to you
hikaru namida wa hohoemi no maebure dakara
Glimmering tears are a prelude to a smile,
itsuka sono kanashimi ni dareka ga tsubasa o kureru deshou
so someday, somebody will give wings to your sadness
kaze ga hoho o nadete yuku
The wind strokes your cheeks
hizashi kimi ni furisosogu
The sunlight streams down on you
egao o omoidashita ne
You remember how to smile, don't you?
dareka no koe ni kotaetan da ne
You've replied to the voice of another, haven't you?
chiisana hohoemi shiawase no maebure dakara
A small smile is a prelude to happiness,
itsuka sono yorokobi ni kimi ga tsutsumareru koto deshou
so someday, you will be enveloped in that joy
tsubasa moratta kanashimi satta kokoro ni
My heart has been given wings and cast sadness aside,
niji wa umareru
bringing forth a rainbow
sabishisa iro kara nukumori iro e
From the color of loneliness to the color of warmth...
sore wa kimochi no guradeeshon
That is the gradation of feelings
atataka na kagayaki o itsu made mo
May that warm glow never fade away...
hontou ni hontou no hitoribocchi nante
You should already know that true, utter loneliness...
doko ni mo inai to iu koto kimi wa mou shitteiru hazu dakara
...does not exist anywhere in the world
dareka no namida ni itsu no hi ka deatta naraba
If someday, you encounter the tears of another...
kondo wa sono kanashimi ni
When such a time comes,
kimi ga tsubasa o ataemashou
you should be the one to give wings to their sadness
tsubasa moratta kanashimi satta kokoro ni
My heart has been given wings and cast sadness aside,
niji wa umareru
bringing forth a rainbow
sabishisa iro kara nukumori iro e
From the color of loneliness to the color of warmth...
sore wa kimochi no guradeeshon
That is the gradation of feelings
atataka na kagayaki o itsu made mo
May that warm glow never fade away...